These are grim economic times,
هذه هي الأوقات الإقتصادية القاتمة
fellow TEDsters, grim economic times indeed.
زملائي في تيد , هذه هي الاوقات القاتمة فعلا.
And so, I would like to cheer you up
ولذلك, أريد أن أبهجكم
with one of the great, albeit largely unknown,
مع موضوع كبير , وان كان مجهولا الى حد بعيد
commercial success stories
قصص النجاح التجاري
of the past 20 years.
على مدى العشرين عاما الماضية
Comparable, in its own very peculiar way,
بالمقارنة, مع الطريقة الخاصة والغريبة جداً,
to the achievements of Microsoft or Google.
لإنجازات ميكروسوفت أو جوجل
And it's an industry which has bucked the current recession
حيث انها من الصناعات التي خالفت الركود الحالي
with equanimity.
برباطة جأش.
I refer to organized crime.
اود الانتقال الى الجريمة المنظمة
Now organized crime has been around
الآن بدأت تنتشر الجريمة المنظمة
for a very long time, I hear you say,
سمعتكم تقولون ذلك لفترة طويلة
and these would be wise words, indeed.
في الواقع ,قد تكون كلمات حكيمة
But in the last two decades,
لكن في العقدين الأخيرين
it has experienced an unprecedented expansion,
شهدت توسعاً لا مثيل له.
now accounting for roughly 15 percent
الآن تستأثر مايقارب 15بالمئة
of the world's GDP.
من الناتج الإجمالي المحلي العالمي.
I like to call it the Global Shadow Economy,
احب ان اسميه إقتصاد الظل العالمي،
or McMafia, for short.
او ائتلاف المافيا , للإختصار.
So what triggered this extraordinary growth
اذا مالذي تسبب في هذا النمو الاستثنائي
in cross-border crime?
في الجريمة العابرة للحدود؟
Well, of course, there is globalization,
حسناً, بالطبع , هناك العولمة.
technology, communications, all that stuff,
التكنولوجيا, الاتصالات , كل هذه الاصناف,
which we'll talk about a little bit later.
والتي سوف نتحدث عنها قليلا في وقت لاحق.
But first, I would like to take you back
ولكن اولا, اود ان اعيدكم للخلف
to this event:
لهذا الحدث
the collapse of communism.
انهيار الشيوعية
All across Eastern Europe, a most momentous episode
في جميع انحاء اوروبا الشرقية, اهم واخطر حلقة
in our post-war history.
في تاريخنا مابعد الحرب
Now it's time for full disclosure.
الان هو الوقت للإفصاح الكامل
This event meant a great deal to me personally.
هذا الحدث يعني الكثير بالنسبة لي شخصيا
I had started smuggling books across the Iron Curtain
كنت قد بدأت تهريب الكتب عبر الستار الحديدي
to Democratic opposition groups in Eastern Europe,
لجماعات المعارضة الديمقراطية في أوروبا الشرقية ،
like Solidarity in Poland,
مثل "التضامن" في بولندا
when I was in my teens.
عندما كنت في سن المراهقة.
I then started writing about Eastern Europe,
بعدها بدأت الكتابة حول اوروبا الشرقية
and eventually I became the BBC's chief correspondent for the region,
واصبحت في نهاية المطاف مراسل البي بي سي لقائد المنطقة
which is what I was doing in 1989.
وهو ماكنت افعله في عام 1989
And so when 425 million people
وهكذا حتى حصل 425 مليون شخص
finally won the right
اخيرا على حق
to choose their own governments,
اختيار حكوماتهم
I was ecstatic,
كنت منتشياً.
but I was also a touch worried
ولكن كنت ايضا قلقاً
about some of the nastier things
حول بعض الامور الشريرة
lurking behind the wall.
المتربصة خلف الجدران
It wasn't long, for example,
على سبيل المثال , لم تكن طويلة
before ethnic nationalism
قبل القومية العرقية
reared its bloody head
حيث اطلت بوجهها الدموي
in Yugoslavia.
في يوغسلافيا
And amongst the chaos,
وبين الفوضى
amidst the euphoria,
وسط الغبطة
it took me a little while to understand
استغرقت فترة للاستيعاب
that some of the people who had wielded power
ان بعض الناس الذين كانو يمارسون السلطة
before 1989, in Eastern Europe,
قبل عام 1989 في اوربا الشرقية
continued to do so after the revolutions there.
واصلوا القيام بذلك بعد الثورات هناك.
Obviously there were characters like this.
من الواضح هناك شخصيات كهذه .
But there were also some more unexpected people
لكن كان هناك أيضاً أناس غير متوقعين إطلاقا
who played a critical role in what was going on in Eastern Europe.
والذين لعبوا الدور الحاسم في مجريات ماكان يحدث في أوربا الشرقية.
Like this character. Remember these guys?
كهذه الشخصية .. هل تتذكرون هؤلاء الشباب ؟
They used to win the gold medals in weightlifting
الذين اعتادوا الفوز بالميداليات الذهبية في مباريات رفع الأثقال
and wrestling, every four years in the Olympics,
والمصارعة كل اربعة اعوام في الالعاب الاولمبية.
and they were the great celebrities of communism,
وكانوا من كبار المشاهير الشيوعيين.
with a fabulous lifestyle to go with it.
مع اسلوب رائع للحياة اندمجوا معها.
They used to get great apartments in the center of town,
إعتياد الحصول على شقة فخمة في وسط المدينة.
casual sex on tap,
وأنواع الجنس المتاح .
and they could travel to the West very freely,
وامكانية السفر للغرب بحرية كبيرة
which was a great luxury at the time.
التي كانت تعتبر رفاهية عالية في ذلك الوقت.
It may come as a surprise, but they played a critical role
قد يكون كلامي مثير للدهشة, ولكنهم لعبوا دورا حاسماً في
in the emergence of the market economy
تحرير إقتصاد السوق
in Eastern Europe.
في أوربا الشرقية
Or as I like to call them, they are
او كما احب أن أسميهم
the midwives of capitalism.
قابلات (مولدات) الرأسمالية.
Here are some of those same weightlifters
هنا بعض نفس رافعي الأثقال هؤلاء
after their 1989 makeover.
بعد تغيرهم 1989
Now in Bulgaria --
الآن في بلغاريا,
this photograph was taken in Bulgaria --
هذه الصورة اخذت في بلغاريا
when communism collapsed all over Eastern Europe,
عندما انهارت الشيوعية في اوربا الشرقية
it wasn't just communism;
لم تكن فقط الشيوعية ,
it was the state that collapsed as well.
بل كانت الدولة التي انهارت ايضا
That means your police force wasn't working.
ذلك يعني ان قوى الشرطة لم تكن تعمل .
The court system wasn't functioning properly.
ونظام المحكمة لم يكن يعمل بشكل صحيح
So what was a business man in the brave new world
فا مالذي كان سيفعله رجل اعمال في عالم جديد
of East European capitalism going to do
من رأسمالية اروبا الشرقيه
to make sure that his contracts would be honored?
ليكون واثقاً من ان عقوده ستحترم ؟
Well, he would turn to people who were called, rather prosaically
حسناً, سيلجأ الى اناس تسمى على غير
by sociologists, privatized law enforcement agencies.
تسمية علم الإجتماع
We prefer to know them as the mafia.
نفضل تعريفهم بالمافيا
And in Bulgaria, the mafia was soon joined
وفي بلغاريا , المافيا كانت مستعدة لتظم
with 14,000 people
14 الف شخص
who were sacked from their jobs in the security services
من من طردوا من اعمالهم بخدمة الأمن
between 1989 and 1991.
بين 1989 و 1991
Now, when your state is collapsing,
الآن عندما تنهار دولتك
your economy is heading south at a rate of knots,
يتجه اقتصادك نحو الإنهيار بسرعة عالية
the last people you want coming on to the labor market
آخر الناس الذين تريدهم أن يدخلو سوق العمالة
are 14,000 men and women whose chief skills
هم 14 ألف رجل وامراة الذين مهاراتهم الأساسية
are surveillance,
هي المراقبة
are smuggling, building underground networks
هي التهريب, بناء شبكات غير مشروعة
and killing people.
وقتل الناس.
But that's what happened all over Eastern Europe.
وهذا ماحدث في انحاء اوربا الغربية كلها
Now, when I was working in the 1990s,
عندما كنت اعمل في سنة 1990
I spent most of the time covering
قضيت معظم الوقت متخفي
the appalling conflict in Yugoslavia.
بسبب الترويع في يوغسلافيا
And I couldn't help notice
ولم استطيع ملاحظة
that the people who were perpetrating the appalling atrocities,
أن الناس الذين كانو يرتكبون الفظائع المروعة,
the paramilitary organizations,
المنظمات شبه العسكرية
were actually the same people running
هم في الواقع نفس الناس الذين يشغلون
the organized criminal syndicates.
جماعات الجريمة المنظمة.
And I came to think that behind the violence
حيث لاحظت ان خلف العنف
lay a sinister criminal enterprise.
يقبع مشروع اجرامي شرير
And so I resolved to travel around the world
ولذلك عزمت على السفر حول العالم
examining this global criminal underworld
لبحث هذه الجريمة العالمية في عالم الإجرام
by talking to policemen,
عبر التحدث للشرطة
by talking to victims, by talking to consumers
للضحايا , لمستهلكي
of illicit goods and services.
السلع والخدمات المحظورة
But above all else, by talking to the gangsters themselves.
وفوق ذلك كله , التحدث لافراد العصابات نفسهم
And the Balkans was a fabulous place to start.
وليس هناك افضل من دول البلقان لأبدأ
Why? Well of course
لماذا ؟ حسناً بالطبع
there was the issue of law and order collapsing,
هناك قضية انهيار القانون والنظام
but also, as they say in the retail trade,
لكن أيضاً, كما يقولون في تجارة التجزئة,
it's location, location, location.
إنها الموقع الموقع الموقع
And what I noticed at the beginning of my research
وما لاحظته في بداية بحثي
that the Balkans had turned into a vast transit zone
أن البلقان قد تحول إلى منطقة عبور للتجارة السوداء
for illicit goods and services coming from all over the world.
بالبضائع والخدمات الغير مشروعة القادمة من جميع أنحاء العالم.
Heroin, cocaine,
الهيروين, الكوكايين,
women being trafficked into prostitution
نساء للتجارة بأجسادهم في البغاء
and precious minerals.
والمعادن النفيسة
And where were they heading?
واين كان هؤلاء يختفون؟
The European Union, which by now
الإتحاد الاوربي, والذي كان
was beginning to reap the benefits of globalization,
في بداية جني ثمار العولمة.
transforming it into
محولاً إياها إلى
the most affluent consumer market in history,
أغنى سوق إستهلاكي في التاريخ.
eventually comprising some 500 million people.
وانتهى بضم 500 مليون نسمة.
And a significant minority
ونطاق كبير
of those 500 million people
من هؤلاء الـ 500 مليون نسمة
like to spend some of their leisure time and spare cash
يحبون إمضاء أوقات الراحة والفراغ
sleeping with prostitutes,
بالنوم مع العاهرات
sticking 50 Euro notes up their nose
يعطونهم 50 يورو بإذلال
and employing illegal migrant laborers.
ويُشغلون العمالة المهاجرة الغير شرعية
Now, organized crime in a globalizing world
الآن, الجريمة المنظمة في ظل العولمة
operates in the same way as any other business.
تستثمر بنفس الطريقة كما الأعمال الأخرى.
It has zones of production,
لديها مناطق إنتاج,
like Afghanistan and Columbia.
كافغانستان وكولومبيا.
It has zones of distribution,
لديها مناطق توزيع
like Mexico and the Balkans.
مثل البلقان والمكسيك
And then, of course, it has zones of consumption,
وبعدها بالطبع لديها مناطق استهلاك
like the European Union, Japan
مثل الإتحاد الاوربي , اليابان
and of course, the United States.
وطبعاً الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية.
The zones of production and distribution
مناطق الإنتاج والتوزيع
tend to lie in the developing world,
تتجه للتمدد في العالم النامي.
and they are often threatened by appalling violence
وعلى الغالب فيهما التهديد بالعنف المروع
and bloodshed.
وسفك الدماء.
Take Mexico, for example.
لنأخذ المكسيك على سبيل المثال.
Six thousand people killed there in the last 18 months
ستة آلاف شخص قتلو هناك في الأشهر 18 الأخيرة
as a direct consequence of the cocaine trade.
كنتيجة مباشرة لتجارة الكوكايين.
But what about the Democratic Republic of Congo?
ولكن ماذا عن جمهورية الكونغو الديمقراطية؟
Since 1998, five million people have died there.
خمسة ملايين شخص ماتوا هناك منذ العام 1998.
It's not a conflict you read about much in the newspapers,
إنه ليس صراعاً تقرؤن عنه كثيرا في الصحف.
but it's the biggest conflict on this planet
لكنه الصراع الأكبر على هذا الكوكب
since the Second World War.
منذ الحرب العالمية الثانية.
And why is it? Because mafias from all around the world
ولماذا هذا الصراع؟ بسبب ان المافيا حول العالم
cooperate with local paramilitaries
تتعاون مع المجموعات المسلحة المحلية
in order to seize the supplies
للإستيلاء على مخزون
of the rich mineral resources
الموارد المعدنية
of the region.
في المنطقة
In the year 2000, 80 percent of the world's coltan
في العام 2000 , 80% من معدن الكولتان في العالم
was sourced to the killing fields
كان مصدرها حقول القتل
of the eastern Democratic Republic of Congo.
في شرق جمهورية الكونغو الديمقراطية
Now, coltan you will find in almost every mobile phone,
والآن تجد معدن الكولتان تقريبا في كل جهاز موبايل,
in almost every laptop
وفي كل جهاز لاب توب
and games console.
وألواح الألعاب
The Congolese war lords were selling this stuff to the mafia
أمراء الحرب الكونغوليين كانو يبيعون هذه الأصناف إلى المافيا
in exchange for weapons,
مقابل السلاح
and the mafia would then sell it on to Western markets.
والمافيا بعد ذلك ستبيعها في الأسواق الغربية.
And it is this Western desire
إنها الرغبة الغربية
to consume
للإستهلاك
that is the primary driver
هذا هو الدافع الرئيسي
of international organized crime.
للجريمة العالمية المنظمة.
Now, let me show you some of my friends in action,
الآن, دعوني أريكم بعض أصدقائي خلال عملية
caught conveniently on film by the Italian police,
القبض عليهم في فيلم بواسطة الشرطة الإيطالية
and smuggling duty-not-paid cigarettes.
وتهريب السجائر الغير مدفوعة نظامياً
Now, cigarettes out the factory gate are very cheap.
الآن السجائر خارج بوابة المصنع رخيصة جداً.
The European Union then imposes the highest taxes on them in the world.
الإتحاد الاوربي بعدها يفرض عليها اعلى الضرائب عالمياً.
So if you can smuggle them into the E.U.,
وهكذا إذا استطعت تهريبها إلى الإتحاد الأوربي.
there are very handsome profits to be made,
فستكون ذات عائد ربحي ممتاز.
and I want to show you this to demonstrate
وأريد أن أريكم هذا لتوضيح
the type of resources available to these groups.
أنواع المصادر المتاحة لهذه المجموعات.
This boat is worth one million Euros when it's new.
هذا القارب يساوي 1 مليون يورو إذا كان جديداً.
And it's the fastest thing on European waters.
وهو أسرع شيء في المياه الأوربية.
From 1994, for seven years,
من العام 1994 إلى 7 سنوات,
20 of these boats
عشرون من هذه القوارب
made the trip across the Adriatic,
قام بالرحلة عبر البحر الأدرياتيكي
from Montenegro to Italy, every single night.
من مونينيجرو إلى إيطاليا, كل ليلة.
And as a consequence of this trade,
وكنتيجة لهذه التجارة
Britain alone lost eight billion dollars in revenue.
خسرت بريطانيا لوحدها 9 مليارات دولار في الدخل الحكومي.
And instead that money went to underwrite the wars in Yugoslavia
وبدلاً من ذلك ذهبت تلك الأموال لتمويل الحروب في يوغوسلافيا
and line the pockets of unscrupulous individuals.
وإلى جيوب أشخاص عديمي الضمير.
Now Italian police, when this trade started,
الآن الشرطة الإيطالية, عندما بدأت هذه التجارة
had just two boats which could go at the same speed.
كان لديهم فقط قاربين يمكنهما السير بنفس السرعة.
And this is very important, because the only way you can catch these guys
وهذا مهم جداً لأن الطريقة الوحيدة للإمساك بهؤلاء الشباب
is if they run out of gas.
هي عندما ينفذ منهم الوقود.
Sometimes the gangsters would bring with them
بعض الأوقات يجلب افراد العصابات معهم
women being trafficked into prostitution,
نساء للتجارة بأجسادهم في البغاء.
and if the police intervened, they would hurl
وإذا تدخلت الشرطة فسيرمون
the women into the sea
النساء في البحر
so that the police had to go and save them from drowning,
وهكذا فعلى الشرطة الذهاب وإنقاذ النساء من الغرق.
rather than chasing the bad guys.
بدلاً من الإمساك بالشباب السيئين.
So I have shown you this to demonstrate
إذا لقد أريتكم هذا للبرهان
how many boats, how many vessels it takes
كم من القوارب, كم من الزوارق تلزم
to catch one of these guys.
للإمساك بواحد من هؤلاء الشباب.
And the answer is six vessels.
والجواب هو 6 زوارق.
And remember, 20 of these speed boats
وتذكر أن 20 من هذه القوارب
were coming across the Adriatic
كانت تأتي عبر البحر الأديرياتيكي
every single night.
كل ليلة
So what were these guys doing with all the money they were making?
إذاَ ماذا كان يصنع هؤلاء الشباب بكل المال الذي يجمعونه؟
Well, this is where we come to globalization,
حسناً, هذا ما أتى بنا إلى العولمة
because that was not just the deregulation of global trade.
لأنها لم تكن مجرد تفادي السلطة في التجارة العالمية.
It was the liberalization of international financial markets.
كانت التحرر من الأسوق المالية الدولية.
And boy, did that make it easy
وذلك ما جعلها سهلة
for the money launderers.
من أجل غاسلي الأموال.
The last two decades have been the champagne era
العقدين الماضيين كانا عصر الإحتفال
for dirty lucre.
بالربح القذر.
In the 1990s, we saw financial centers around the world
في التسعينات شاهدنا المراكز المالية حول العالم
competing for their business,
تتنافس لاجل أعمالهم.
and there was simply no effective mechanism
وببساطة لم يكن موجود أي تقنية ناجعة
to prevent money laundering.
لمنع غسيل الأموال.
And a lot of licit banks were also happy
ومع ذلك كانت كثير من البنوك الشرعية سعيدة
to accept deposits
بقبول الودائع
from very dubious sources
من كل المصادر المشبوهة
without questions being asked.
بدون وجود أي مُسائلة.
But at the heart of this, is the offshore banking network.
لكن في قلب هذا, الشبكات البنكية الأجنبية.
Now these things
الآن هذه الأشياء
are an essential part of the money laundering parade,
هي الجزء الأساسي في مسيرة غسيل الأموال.
and if you want to do something about illegal tax evasion
إذا أردت أن تقوم بشيئ حول التملص الضريبي الغير شرعي
and transnational organized crime, money laundering,
والجريمة المنظمة العابرة للحدود وغسيل الأموال
you have to get rid of them.
فيجب عليك التخلص من تلك الأشياء
On a positive note, we at last have someone in the White House
من ناحية إيجابية لدينا في نهاية المطاف شخص في البيت الأبيض
who has consistently spoken out
يتكلم دائما بدون خوف
against these corrosive entities.
ضد هذه الكيانات المتآكلة.
And if anyone is concerned about what I believe
وإذا كان لاحد قلق إزاء ما أعتقد
is the necessity for
للحاجة الملحة
new legislation, regulation, effective regulation,
لقوانين جديدة وتشريعات فعالة
I say, let's take a look at Bernie Madoff,
فأنا أرد, دعونا نلقي نظرة على بيرني مادوف
who is now going to be spending the rest of his life in jail.
الذي سيمضي ماتبقى من حياته في السجن.
Bernie Madoff stole 65 billion dollars.
سرق بيرني مادوف 65 مليار دولار.
That puts him up there on the Olympus of gangsters
مما يضعه في قمة رجال العصابات
with the Colombian cartels
بالمقارنة مع الجماعات الكولومبية,
and the major Russian crime syndicates,
وأهم عصابات الإجرام الروسية.
but he did this for decades
لكنه فعل هذا على مدار عقود
in the very heart of Wall Street,
في قلب وول ستريت.
and no regulator picked up on it.
ولم يتم أي ضبط لهذا.
So how many other Madoffs are there on Wall Street
إذاً كم مادوف لدينا في وول ستريت
or in the city of London,
أو في لندن
fleecing ordinary folk
ينهبون الناس العاديين
and money laundering?
ويغسلون الأموال؟
Well I can tell you, it's quite a few of them.
حسناً يمكنني إخباركم أن القليل منهم يكفي تماماً.
Let me go on to the 101 of international organized crime now.
دعوني أتابع إلى العدد 1 بعد 100 من الجريمة الدولية المنظمة الآن.
And that is narcotics. Our second marijuana farm photograph for the morning.
وتلك هي المواد المخدرة. صورنا الثانية لمزرعة المارغونا في الصباح.
This one, however, is in central British Columbia
هذه على أي حال في وسط كولومبيا البريطانية (مقاطعة في غرب كندا)
where I photographed it.
حيث قمت بتصويرها.
It's one of the tens of thousands
إنها واحدة من عشرات الآلاف
of mom-and-pop grow-ops in B.C.
من مشاريع المخدرات الناشئة في كولومبيا البريطانية
which ensure that over five percent
والتي تُأكد أن اكثر من 5 بالمئة
of the province's GDP is accounted for by this trade.
من الناتج المحلي الإجمالي هو من نصيب هذه التجارة.
Now, I was taken by inspector Brian Cantera,
الآن أنا مع المفتش برين سينترا
of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police,
من الشرطة الملكية الكندية
to a cavernous warehouse east of Vancouver
إلى مستودع مخفي في شرق "فانكوفر"
to see some of the goods which are regularly confiscated
لمشاهدة بعض البضائع المصادرة
by the RCMP
بواسطة الشرطة الملكية الكندية
from the smugglers who are sending it,
من المهربين الذين يرسلونها
of course, down south to the United States
بالطبع إلى الجنوب إلى الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية
where there is an insatiable market
الذي يعتبر السوق النَهِم
for B.C. Bud, as it's called,
لكولمبيا البريطانية كما تسمى "برعم"
in part because it's marketed as organic,
بشكل جزئي لانه يتم تسويقها على أنها عضوية
which of course goes down very well in California.
التي سريعا ما تذهب للاسفل في كاليفورنيا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now, even by the police's admission,
الآن حتى مع تصريح الشرطة
this makes not a dent in the profits, really,
هذا لايؤدي حقاً لإنخفاض أرباح
of the major exporters.
المُصدرين الرئيسيين.
Since the beginning of globalization,
منذ بداية العولمة
the global narcotics market has expanded enormously.
بدأت سوق المخدرات تنتشر عالمياً بشكل هائل
There has, however, been no concomitant increase
ومع ذلك فلم يكن هناك أي زيادة
in the resources available
في المصادر المتوفرة
to police forces.
لقوى الشرطة.
This, however, may all be about to change,
لكن قد يتغير هذا كله قريباً
because something very strange is going on.
لأن شيء غريب جداً يحصل.
The United Nations recognized
لاحظت الأمم المتحدة
earlier this -- it was last month actually --
هذا مبكرا في الواقع كان هذا في الشهر الماضي
that Canada has become a key area of distribution and production
حيث أصبحت كندا المنطقة الاساسية لإنتاج وتوزيع
of ecstasy and other synthetic drugs.
عقاقير النشوة والمخدرات الصناعية الأخرى.
Interestingly, the market share
الطريف أن حصة السوق
of heroin and cocaine is going down,
من الهيرويين والكوكايين تنخفض
because the pills are getting ever better at reproducing their highs.
بسبب التقدم الغير مسبوق للحبيبات في إعادة إنتاجها.
Now that is a game changer,
الآن ذلك هو مُغير اللعبة.
because it shifts production away from the developing world
لأنه ينقل الإنتاج بعيداً عن العالم النامي
and into the Western world.
إلى العالم الغربي.
When that happens, it is a trend
عندما يحصل فهذا سيشكل توجه
which is set to overwhelm our policing capacity in the West.
هدفه القضاء على قدرتنا في حفظ الأمن في الغرب.
The drugs policy which we've had in place for 40 years
تشريعات المخدرات التي لدينا منذ 40 سنة
is long overdue for a very serious rethink,
اصبحت متأخرة وبحاجة لإعادة تفكير بشكل جدي
in my opinion.
حسب رأيي الشخصي.
Now, the recession.
الآن الركود الإقتصادي.
Well, organized crime has already adapted
حسناً, لقد تأقلمت الجريمة المنظمة
very well to the recession.
مع الركود الإقتصادي بشكل جيد جداً.
Not surprising, the most opportunistic industry
ولا عجب, الصناعة الأكثر إنتهازية
in the whole world.
في العالم كله.
And it has no rules to its regulatory system.
وليس لديها أي مبادىء في نظامها التشريعي
Except, of course, it has two business risks:
إلا أنه طبعاً لديها اثنين من المخاطر التجارية,
arrest by law enforcement,
إلقاء القبض بواسطة القوانين المفروضة
which is, frankly, the least of their worries,
والتي بكل صراحة أقل مايقلقون بشأنه,
and competition from other groups,
والمنافسة من المجموعات الأخرى,
i.e. a bullet in the back of the head.
أي رصاصة قاتلة في الرأس.
What they've done is they've shifted their operations.
ما قاموا به هو تحريك عملياتهم.
People don't smoke as much dope, or visit prostitutes quite so frequently
الناس لا تدخن كثيراً كما يتعاطون المخدرات أو يزورون العاهرات بشكل متكرر تماما
during a recession.
خلال فترة الركود الإقتصادي.
And so instead, they have invaded financial
وهكذا فهم عوضا عن ذلك اجتاحوا الإقتصاد
and corporate crime in a big way,
واسسوا الجريمة بصورة كبيرة
but above all, two sectors,
لكن بداية الأمر قطاعين اثنين
and that is counterfeit goods
وهي البضائع المزيفة
and cybercrime.
والجرائم الحاسوبية.
And it's been terribly successful.
وتنجح بشق الانفس.
I would like to introduce you to Mr. Pringle.
أود أن أقدم لكم السيد برينجل.
Or perhaps I should say, more accurately, Señor Pringle.
أو ربما يجب أن أقول بشكل اوضح سينيور برينجل.
I was introduced to this bit of kit by a Brazilian cybercriminal.
وكنت قد بدات التعرف على هذه الاداة بواسطة مجرم انترنت برازيلي
We sat in a car on the Avenue Paulista
جلسنا في سيارة في "جادة بوليستا"
in São Paulo, together.
مع بعضنا في "سانباولو."
Hooked it up to my laptop,
ألحقتها في جهازي المحمول
and within about five minutes he had penetrated
وخلال حوالي 5 دقائق قام باختراق
the computer security system
نظام الحماية الحاسوبي
of a major Brazilian bank.
للبنك البرازيلي الرئيسي.
It's really not that difficult.
إنها ليست بتلك الصعوبة حقاً.
And it's actually much easier because
بل في الواقع اسهل بكثير لأن
the fascinating thing about cybercrime
الشيء الساحر حول جرائم الحاسوب
is that it's not so much the technology.
هو أنها ليست تكنولوجية بشكل كبير.
The key to cybercrime is what we call social engineering.
المفتاح للجرائم الحاسوبية هو مانسميه هندسة التكاثر.
Or to use the technical term for it,
أو لنستخدم المصطلح التقني لها,
there's one born every minute.
كل دقيقة يوجد جديد.
You would not believe how easy it is
لن تصدق مدى سهولة
to persuade people to do things with their computers
إقناع الناس بفعل أشياء مع حواسيبهم
which are objectively not in their interest.
التي بموضوعية لاتلبي اهتماماتهم.
And it was very soon
وكانت قريبة جداً
when the cybercriminals learned that the quickest way to do this,
عندما تعلم مجرموا الانترنت الطريقة الأسرع لفعل هذا
of course, the quickest way to a person's wallet
بالطبع الطريقة الأسرع لمحفظة الشخص
is through the promise of sex and love.
هي عبر الوعد بالحب والجنس.
I expect some of you remember the ILOVEYOU virus,
أتوقع ان بعضكم يتذكر فيروس "أنا أحبك"
one of the very great worldwide viruses that came.
أكثر الفيروسات إنتشارا حول العالم.
I was very fortunate when the ILOVEYOU virus came out,
كنت سعيد الحظ كثيراً عندما ظهر فيروس "انا أحبك"
because the first person I received it from
لأن أول شخص تسلمت منه الفيروس
was an ex-girlfriend of mine.
كان صديقتي الحميمة السابقة.
Now, she harbored all sorts of sentiments and emotions towards me at the time,
الآن أخفت كل أنواع العواطف والمشاعر نحوي في ذلك الوقت
but love was not amongst them.
لكن الحب لم يكن من بينها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so as soon as I saw this drop into my inbox,
حالما رأيت هذه في صندوق الرسائل عندي
I dispatched it hastily to the recycle bin
أرسلتها بسرعة لسلة المحذوفات
and spared myself a very nasty infection.
وانجيت نفسي من العدوى المؤذية.
So, cybercrime, do watch out for it.
إذاً خذو حذركم من الجريمة الحاسوبية.
One thing that we do know that the Internet is doing
شيء واحد نعلمه عن مايفعله الإنترنت
is the Internet is assisting these guys.
هو أن الإنترنت يساعد هؤلاء الشباب.
These are mosquitos who carry the malarial parasite
هذه هي البعوض التي تحمل طفيليات الملاريا
which infests our blood when the mosy has had a free meal
والتي تغزو دمائنا عندما تحصل البعوضة على وجبة مجانية
at our expense.
على حسابنا.
Now, Artesunate is a very effective drug
الآن "الارتيسونيت" هو عقار فعال
at destroying the parasite in the early days
في تدمير الطفيليات في الايام الأولى
of infection.
من الإصابة.
But over the past year or so,
لكن خلال السنة الماضية أو نحوها
researchers in Cambodia have discovered
اكتشف الباحثون في "كمبوديا"
that what's happening is
أن ما يحصل هو
the malarial parasite is developing a resistance.
أن طفيليات الملاريا تطور مقاومتها.
And they fear that the reason why it's developing a resistance
وهم يخافون أن السبب في تطويرها للمقاومة
is because Cambodians can't afford the drugs on the commercial market,
هو بسبب عدم قدرة الكمبوديين على شراء العقاقير في السوق التجاري
and so they buy it from the Internet.
وهكذا فهم يشترونها عن طريق الإنترنت.
And these pills contain only low doses
وهذه العقاقير تحتوي فقط على جرعات قليلة
of the active ingredient.
من العنصر الفعال.
Which is why
وهذا يفسر لماذا
the parasite is beginning to develop a resistance.
بدأت الطفيليات في تطوير المقاومة.
The reason I say this
الهدف من قولي لهذا
is because we have to know
هو يجب علينا معرفة
that organized crime
أن الجريمة المنظمة
impacts all sorts of areas of our lives.
تؤثر في جميع مجالات حياتنا.
You don't have to sleep with prostitutes
ليس من الواجب عليك النوم مع العاهرات
or take drugs
أو تناول المخدرات
in order to have a relationship with organized crime.
لكي تكون على علاقة مع الجريمة المنظمة.
They affect our bank accounts.
إنهم يؤثرون في حساباتنا البنكية.
They affect our communications, our pension funds.
يؤثرون في شبكات إتصالنا وفي معاشاتنا
They even affect the food that we eat
يؤثرون حتى في الطعام الذي نأكله
and our governments.
وفي حكوماتنا.
This is no longer an issue
هذه لم تعد قضية
of Sicilians from Palermo and New York.
الصيقليين من "باليرمو" و "نيو يورك"
There is no romance involved with gangsters
لايوجد هناك تعامل رومانسي مع العصابات
in the 21st Century.
في القرن الواحد والعشرين.
This is a mighty industry,
هذه صناعة هائلة
and it creates instability and violence
كما أنها تنشئ عدم الإستقرار والعنف
wherever it goes.
اينما ذهبت.
It is a major economic force
إنها القوة الإقتصادية الرئيسية
and we need to take it very, very seriously.
وعلينا التعامل معها بشكل جدي جداً جداً.
It's been a privilege talking to you.
كان من الشرف التحدث إليكم.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)